[SPEAKER_04]: So, it is a common idea in the world that everyone wants to be happy.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, it is easy to approach the Buddha's teaching with the wish, may this make me happy.
[SPEAKER_04]: But what people might overlook is that the desire to be happy can easily become
[SPEAKER_04]: An activity, or dependent upon activity.
[SPEAKER_04]: I do this, which is then, in a positive sense, going to make me happy.
[SPEAKER_04]: But those activities, in their very nature, depend on all sorts of other things that are typically not in your control.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the Buddha's teaching is actually not so much about becoming happy, but about being free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: But what's the difference?
[SPEAKER_00]: Anyone?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, one difference might be that if I'm looking for happiness, I will actively, constantly looking for something outside of what is present now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Instead of, like, if I'm looking to put an end to suffering, I start with what I have, meaning I'm suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I'm looking for happiness, because I'm suffering right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if I start to try to
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the very wish to be happy is actually born from suffering, per se.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, if someone looks for happiness, it's because he's not happy, so he's suffering in a way.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, rather than positively doing something in order to become happy, one can also ask the question, what is it that is presently making me unhappy, and then looking into the origin of that.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that obviously is going to be unpleasant, because one now has to come to terms with the fact that one is not happy.
[SPEAKER_01]: And with the fact that the things that are making you unhappy are precisely the things that you don't want to give up.
[SPEAKER_04]: The things that make you unhappy are the things that you do not want to give up.
[SPEAKER_04]: Ironically enough.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So people... so that means that people are confused about what is actually in their welfare and making them happy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what are the things, then, that one would ordinarily assume make one happy, but that, according to the dhamma, are actually making one suffer?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, I was going to give the coarse example of the triad sex, drugs, and rock and roll.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, yeah, those kind of coarser things that go against the precepts are...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's kind of the first thing that one needs to kind of question, if they want to go in this direction.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, actually, observing eight precepts would be bringing about the right kind of happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Immediately.
[SPEAKER_01]: Immediately, you're saying?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no, I'm asking a rhetorical question.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, if you're approaching the whole question of how can I be happy as quickly as possible, would the eight precepts be the answer?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, because otherwise everybody would be pursuing these decks.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but then the question might arise, so why is it that those things that...
[SPEAKER_01]: That you think are happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it that they're suffering, actually?
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is the difference between the right kind of happiness and the happiness that you get from those things?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you actually get some sort of happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: As Buddha said, it's not that there isn't any gratification in sensuality, because if that were not the case, nobody would be... if that were the case, nobody would be pursuing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it would be just obvious to any anyone that this is not worth it, but it's not like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it does give a factual sort of satisfaction, but what is the difference between that satisfaction and the happiness that you would get from the dhamma?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which, as the Buddha said, nibbāna is the highest happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what was the difference between those two?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the first one is drawing one's attention away from the nature of one's experience or the common thread of all experience and is, yeah,
[SPEAKER_00]: Investing one in that which is dangerous or that which is subject to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: What if you still don't see that taking taking yourself away from the nature of the experience is suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there a more acute reason or more acute difference in the nature of, like, in and of itself, what that happiness is?
[SPEAKER_01]: The wrong happiness and the right happiness.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, the wrong happiness depends on things in the world.
[SPEAKER_04]: Such as?
[SPEAKER_04]: Things that your senses present, for example.
[SPEAKER_04]: More acutely.
[SPEAKER_04]: Content of experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: More acutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, more acutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: More acutely still, eh?
[SPEAKER_01]: Safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, more specifically... Like not being bothered?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, the wrong happiness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, like...
[SPEAKER_03]: Not being bothered just like as a circumstance.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's like you mean ignorance, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And how would you call that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just in the... what would be the simplest label that you could give to that?
[SPEAKER_04]: Delusion?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or greed?
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the wrong type of happiness, because you might say,
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, as you said, there's a course level where you're actively pursuing stuff like in the world and that that's abandoned through the eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not that someone who gives that up already got the right type of happiness because
[SPEAKER_01]: For example, you can be keeping the eight precepts and still be engaging in concentration practices that give you the wrong type of happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like things in the world, in that core sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the fact that it depends on pleasant feeling being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the main problem with that type of happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's based on what you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas the the right type of happiness
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there, regardless of what you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why you wouldn't really call it happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, in a kind of colloquial sense, you could use that expression.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the difference is that it's not... it's about not being bothered on a different level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, circumstantially, pleasant feeling arose.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's even when the most unpleasant feeling arises, you're still not bothered.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why the suttas would say, the liberated mind, whatever feeling it feels, it feels it detached, whether it's pleasant, painful or neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't say that it only feels pleasant feeling, and that's the main distinction.
[SPEAKER_01]: An ordinary person, all they know, in order to... the only way they have to be at peace, even if they're not seeking external pleasures, is to have pleasant feeling enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: If painful feeling is enduring, they cannot be at ease.
[SPEAKER_04]: And... No, on the contrary, this is when they will be seeking pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, in any way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter if, like, they can be seeking pleasant feeling through what they think the dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's still wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's still... if it depends on circumstance, if it depends on things that are impermanent, such as feeling, it's not the dhamma then.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, more acutely, it's... the right happiness is not depending on feeling anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as we already clarified in that discussion about the nature... the difference between feeling, sensations and emotions,
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when you think feelings are just sensations or something, it's quite... the problem is watered down to a great degree.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you understand, feeling is... like, feeling is that... that pressure, that thing, that existential drive, burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you recognize that you're subject to that no matter what, and you can't get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize now that you need to find a way to be at ease even while that burden is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like as Sariputta said, all feelings are suffering in and of themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha gave this simile for the nutriment of contact or pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said it's like a cow that wherever it
[SPEAKER_01]: It would lean on, it would be bitten by gnats and flies and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he says in the same way, it's like we're attacked by pressure, attacked by... And then he said whoever understands that, they understand the three feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's that existential burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: that you can't get rid of.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just a sensation that comes and you sort of do this and that and get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like your entire being is enclosed within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the right happiness would be where, instead of like replacing it with something else, you
[SPEAKER_01]: Understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: First and foremost, understanding that you're subject to this and you don't have a say in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that already would, if you really understand it, that would already seriously diminish the burden because, as the Buddha said, the burden is craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the fact that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Contrary to the fact that it's obviously not in your control, like you've been doing every single... from the day you were born and before, you've been doing everything you could to get rid of it, and yet, not once have you succeeded for any, like, prolonged period of time.
[SPEAKER_01]: In spite of that, you still... no, this time it'll work.
[SPEAKER_01]: This time I'll get it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it never does.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just understanding that this is not in your control, rightly, is already diminishing the burden while the feeling is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, most of the time, for people, finding peace is more like, well, I've been eating this really bitter food, and now I just find this, you know, sweet, creamy ice cream.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the pleasant feeling that people get from, you know, their meditation and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just replacing the other stuff that they would have.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not really making them
[SPEAKER_01]: It's imperturbable, so that even when unpleasant feeling arises, they won't be bothered.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, I'll be at peace only for as long as this pleasant feeling endures.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's still suffering, because you have to maintain it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that's the difficulty.
[SPEAKER_04]: The ordinary conception of happiness is dependent, bound up with doing things that need to be maintained.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as you said just now, it depends on the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yes, sure, but there's... we have to remember that the Buddha also defined the world as in a more acute manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you... if it depends on the five aggregates, it obviously depends on the world already, like, you know, car, family, house and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is also within the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that is the world, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if your happiness depends on pleasant feeling,
[SPEAKER_01]: In and of itself, that's really, like, the root of the issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, pleasant feeling is a dart, painful feeling is a deadly arrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasant feeling should be seen as painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unpleasant feeling should be seen as a dart.
[SPEAKER_01]: And neutral feeling as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you should see the pleasant feeling in and of itself, not as something you find safety in.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter how pleasant it is,
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it comes from something that seems seemingly not external, if it's coming from your meditation, for example, you should still see it as something that you shouldn't rest on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because to the extent that you find safety in pleasant feeling, you are, for that very reason, making yourself unsafe.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only true type of safety or ease is when your mind has been developed to the point that
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if that feeling were to go next second, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: That pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, even if the unpleasant feeling were to last for two million years, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the right type of ease.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, we're talking about feelings here, not sensations.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's that existential burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize it's quite a task to develop yourself to the point where that thing which is almost automatically
[SPEAKER_01]: The most personal, kind of deeply felt thing is not a burden anymore while it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of the time, or 99% of the time, the approach towards it would be, how do I kind of decrease the weight of this, so that it doesn't make me suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's again management.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to see the full weight of feeling, the full weight of sickness, aging and death, as we were discussing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that that goes.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's actually the sutta where Ānanda was...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think he was bathing with the Buddha or something in the river.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he noticed that... he mentioned that the Buddhist skin was already getting wrinkly and old.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha exclaimed the verse saying like, you know, you wretched, wicked, aging, damn you or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, look at how you make this body, you know, that used to be strong and healthy, how it deteriorates.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it means like he still recognized that existential significance of that burden, this pleasure of being subject to aging, but his mind was totally unaffected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the right level of happiness, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, like, a person might think, like, or write happiness, ah, well, whatever, I don't care about this.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, that's replacing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's more like, there was unpleasant feeling and you replace it with something else by, oh, no, this is, this is just, you know, this doesn't exist or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, as we were saying, denying the significance of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, this body is just a pile of atoms or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter if it ages or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Meaning, that's really, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Under the hood approach of you replacing the feeling that was there, in order to find...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all of that happens because the the dominant feeling is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a response to it, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, the right happiness would come from
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you have been enduring the right type of suffering long enough, that we discussed before, suffering that's there on its own, not that you were seeking it by practicing self-mortification, but that you simply stopped the cover-up, like you stopped engaging in the cover-up strategies that you used to have, that suffering that arises once you endure it long enough, so that your mind basically
[SPEAKER_01]: It comes down from that natural tendency to want to outrun it at any price, at any, like, whichever way it can.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, the task is to understand it, to see, as you said, to learn how to see the arising of that feeling in and of itself, whether it's pleasant, unpleasant, neutral, as a
[SPEAKER_01]: Unsafe, like a hot coal that you don't want to touch.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you have no say in it being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you realize that if you grab it, either to get rid of it when it's unpleasant, or to, you know, hold on to it when it's pleasant, that's why you suffer.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, because then, you are basically taking up that feeling and regarding it as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and then,
[SPEAKER_01]: If the unpleasant feeling lasts for too long, that's going to be a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the pleasant feeling doesn't last long enough, or goes away, that's going to be a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's also going to be a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why you don't want even the most seemingly harmless feeling of, you know, you've been keeping the precepts, you've been sense-restrained,
[SPEAKER_01]: That neutral feeling arises, let's say, as the suttas would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it says even that you should see as not worth leaning on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should see it as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_04]: And this is how one comes to see, in fact, impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In regards to those feelings, not again like random sensations, secondary things that don't carry any existential meaning, but with feeling, that is that, as the Buddha said, it's the converging point of your whole existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like the...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's what the dhamma centers around, really.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, the Buddha taught the dhamma to those who feel, he said.
[SPEAKER_04]: And also, he said, those who fully understand feeling, that's basically the definition of an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and then, not like those who don't feel anything anymore or something like... Because, you know, there's this idea as well, I think we discussed it before, like bare perception or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, really, what you're saying is, I will be happy by replacing all these feelings with a blank nothingness, and then that's so...
[SPEAKER_01]: But, see, that's... all of that is just not really seeing that the craving was the root of the issue, not what you were feeling.
[SPEAKER_04]: Although there is that sutta where Sariputta describes that as his conversation with Sariputta, and then he does say, like,
[SPEAKER_04]: How exactly does it go?
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a question about nibbāna, and then he says nothing is felt there.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that is seen, actually, as pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that is then frequently misconstrued in the sense like, I shouldn't feel anything.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, but it's actually, those feelings are still there, but one dwells detached from it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, in that sense, there's no longer feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so, you could say...
[SPEAKER_01]: Without getting too abstract, like, yeah, being disconnected from feelings...
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, it's not like nibbāna is something outside of your aggregates or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still, if you say it's pleasant, it has to be a pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not going to be something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not on the same level where you're replacing stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you achieve it by being able to fully endure the burden of what's actually there, not what you think should be there, based on your preconceived notions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, you know, the precepts and stuff are just not optional, because that puts you in touch with that suffering that you're supposed to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas if you're not keeping that, you can think all you want about not managing feelings and enduring feelings on the right level, but your actions are already the
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, if you don't keep the Eight Precepts, you don't know what feeling is, like, accurately.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not able to feel properly, because as soon as you feel, you do something to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what actions that break the Eight Precepts automatically do.
[SPEAKER_01]: They allow you a little sort of backdoor, when you can
[SPEAKER_01]: Outrun feelings that arise and you don't get to see them for what they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's so important to not do those things, because then, you know, all the dhamma practice you do, it just won't be... regardless of it, you won't be able to understand that those feelings were not the issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you were truly developing the understanding that it's the craving that's the issue, why would you go ahead and still give in?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe we could just... Like, I hear many times, like, people say, like, yeah, but I see it, I focus on my breath, and then I calm my mind, and then I can contemplate the nature of feeling and things like that, and how, like, this practice actually, instead of making one able to see his mind, actually leads him away from that recognition of seeing his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so the thing is, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: You can... the contemplation of... People could say, I'm contemplating my feelings, but the thing is, there's obviously various layers to feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can grab like secondary feelings that don't actually matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: For example, when you're doing breath observation, you can watch your feelings on the level of how your breath makes you feel or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can be contemplating on that very specific level, like, how when I'm breathing, you know, if I breathe this way, I feel like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I breathe that way, it feels like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that's how I'm supposedly contemplating feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I assure you, nobody is like, you know...
[SPEAKER_01]: Doing breath contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, suddenly, that takes them all the way back to question, like, you know, sickness, aging, and death.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just doesn't, because you can't focus yourself in that direction and then still keep sight of that stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might be contemplating feeling, but on a level that doesn't really matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, the super particular present moments sort of stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the background of your entire existence, that you could die at any moment, that you don't have control over this body,
[SPEAKER_01]: That, you know, everything you do fundamentally in this life, won't really amount to anything, because you will die anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be contemplating those feelings, because in order to be focused... like, going in that direction, would actually destroy the calmness that you have, because it's based on ignoring those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: That's actually one criteria that you could use for something that's most likely the right type of peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like you can really go in this direction of contemplating death, aging, things that people's meditation is usually not based on, and it would actually increase the happiness and the peace, not like destroy it because
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, usually people, like, thinking about the future is too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, during their meditation, they stop thinking, focus on the present moments only.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now imagine, like, you start thinking about, you know, your family members dying or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: This sort of contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's gonna destroy the happiness that you have.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it's the right type of peace,
[SPEAKER_01]: It will actually disconnect you from feelings even more.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will place you in that independence of feeling, which is the real happiness or safety, you could say.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, could you say that, like, the people who are... because I hear this a lot as well, people, yeah, saying like, oh, I'm calming my mind, but it's it's not actually their mind that they're calming.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's...
[SPEAKER_03]: Things that they're trying to calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, they're... it's things that they're secondary to their mind, that they're actually calming.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, like the dog is being... the wild dog, the analogy that I always use, it just... you put the wild dog in a special room, that has only the things that will not provoke it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you take it out of that room.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's gonna be exactly the same condition as it was before.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just like managing, manipulating, and interfering with your feelings, with these very specific feelings, so that you don't have to cope with the broader picture of what your life is, what you're subject to, the danger of just being born, the fact that you could die.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's never too late to... too early to die, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: And...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so, if your calmness... because, see, that's a funny thing, like, even in the... like, people are aware sometimes of these contemplations of death and sickness and the corpse contemplations and stuff, but how do they do it?
[SPEAKER_01]: They take it as an object, like a nimitta, image, magical image that you focus on in your mind, and you just keep... and the whole significance and burden of you being subject to death, of your possessions that are going to be lost,
[SPEAKER_01]: Of your loved ones that you will never see again.
[SPEAKER_01]: All that is totally just taken off the picture.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now it's just this object of a dead corpse that I keep repeating or, you know, focusing on as a quasi-mantra.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why then it could give rise to that same, again, wrong kind of peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it's that right contemplation of death where you're truly acknowledging
[SPEAKER_01]: While you're acknowledging the size of your attachments and the pleasures that you cherish, at the same time, you're countering it with the liability to abrupt and immediate destruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if that gives rise to peace, that's that independence from feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is actually like... You know, like, there's no doubt that if you...
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing beyond that, then this could still disturb you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: And also, that's how your attachments come into sight in the first place.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you want to have that other direction and attempt... basically, this is then yoniso.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, attempt from the origin.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is where hindrances and attachment in the other direction come to be seen.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that is the direction which is experientially gonna be like death.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because in that direction, is there anything that you can take up and regard as yours, fundamentally?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and that's really the difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can say the contemplation can either go in the direction of
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeking peace by ignoring your liability to suffering, which is that inauthenticity that we discussed before.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all sensual pleasures, partake of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can get peace by, essentially, by forgetting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, ignorance is bliss, as they say.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can go in that direction, or you can
[SPEAKER_01]: Become properly aware of that liability to suffering, not just by thinking about it, but by factually abandoning the actions that are based and fully centered around covering up that liability.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when you expose yourself to it long enough, allow it to endure, don't distract yourself from it and try to get rid of it by impulse, then your contemplation takes you in the direction of
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding that liability.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that's a completely different thing, because you didn't try to take a shortcut.
[SPEAKER_01]: You didn't try to... Like, it's actually the aggregate of feeling that you understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not now some secondary thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, it's kind of like... You could say it's almost like... How do you call those?
[SPEAKER_01]: When you make...
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a model of a city before they actually build it.
[SPEAKER_04]: A maquette.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a little sort of thing that's supposed to be a representation of the real thing, but actually it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's kind of like the feelings that people are contemplating during their meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a...
[SPEAKER_01]: Representation, supposedly, of the bigger thing, but it's not actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the bigger stuff, you entered your practice by ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it looks to you like, yeah, this is the actual city, it's not.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, and for those people who might already be established in some sort of practice or other, one way to find out if they're doing it right, is to stop doing that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not the precepts, but their methods and techniques, and then see if that disturbs the mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: If it does, you know for a fact that what you think the practice is, is actually creating this artificial peace on the level of a maquette in front of you, as you just described it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing is that...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know why, like, people don't realize this is already a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the fact that I have to keep maintaining this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That should be obvious enough, like, you know, it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's already going away, if I stop doing it for a few weeks... Then what's gonna happen when you get sick and die?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but there is this kind of magical view that if I keep doing it long enough,
[SPEAKER_01]: Eventually, at some point, there's going to be this click where it's never going to go away.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, if you're developing the right type of peace, even, like, not all the way to enlightenment, just some amount of taming of the mind on account of virtue, on account of sensory strength, and watching your intentions and not giving in to them, that's something that would endure
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, for as long as you don't go and break the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nothing else would need to be done to maintain that sort of happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it does have a...
[SPEAKER_01]: It is much less palpable in the beginning, maybe, but it does have a much more lasting nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's not full-on, like, even without the Buddha, you know, like, there were these...
[SPEAKER_01]: There were ascetics before the Buddha who would also develop samādhi and stuff, which you could say is the right... already in the nature of the right type of happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not concentration, but basically immovability of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that's already... that would... they would already have that ability to
[SPEAKER_01]: Be at ease with having to constantly engage in two hours of something every day.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's basically depending on you... Not engaging with those things that disturb the mind, rather than having to do things in order to make your mind peaceful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not doing things that distract you from your liability to suffering, would sustain that peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is...
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, the liability to suffering is the reason for you being at peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the counterintuitive nature of...
[SPEAKER_04]: The liability to suffering is the reason why you would dwell at peace.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, if that suffering has been understood correctly and you're not craving for or against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the liability to suffering reminds you, if you have understood it rightly, reminds you of
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just the same as saying that all the Four Noble Truths, they basically... it's one thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, that cannot be the Noble Truth of Suffering without at the same time knowing its origin and its cessation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Really, you are already experiencing the liberation from it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, because without being liberated from it, you would not be able to see the totality of what is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's mutually sustaining, the liberation and the recognition of what suffering is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, that's very different from saying that you get rid of it or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still there, but the fact that you understand it means that it can't... A craving can only exist when there is ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And ignorance is not some magical energy.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not understanding feelings, you can say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not understanding their extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not understanding their magnitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not being able to see them for what they are, while they endure, that's the... that's what ignorance is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And just that, you don't need to then decide or have some, like, accident where, oh, crap, then I was ignorant and then something else happened and then I started craving against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: The presence of ignorance is the presence of craving, immediately.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not knowing... not knowing feelings means craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Immediately.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, at the same time, the opposite applies.
[SPEAKER_04]: Knowing feelings, knowing their impermanence, knowing that all of them are suffering, even if they're pleasant, that, at the same time, means there's no room for craving there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that should be your standard.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do I know whether I have been cultivating the true freedom from craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, is it enough when a feeling is there, no matter its kind?
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't manage it, I didn't try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it enough for me just to know the nature of that feeling in order to be completely unaffected by it, without having to go through some secondary motions?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you would know whether you're getting closer to it or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Going back a little bit on what you were saying, like, when you say, if someone really recognizes this is suffering, he experiences already the liberation from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that's the difficulty, because I can say, yeah, all of that is impermanence, this is suffering, but actually, if I don't experience the liberation from it, it's because I don't see it for what it is, really.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's very easy, like, to fool him... one to fool himself about that, because
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if someone really recognizes something...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, if someone, for example, is smoking and he really sees that he's very unbeneficial from it, he gives it up right away.
[SPEAKER_02]: He doesn't have to wait some, like, medicine or some, I don't know, doing some sport or something around it in order to understand that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's very... Yeah, I think there is, like, quite...
[SPEAKER_02]: I want to say quite some...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's very easy to see, to think like, oh, I understand, this is suffering, but actually not.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing is, yeah, so that's one of the... that's why there's this idea of, oh, I recognize the suffering and I have to let go of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, that's already on the level of management.
[SPEAKER_01]: If
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, for you, in that context, letting go would mean, how do I replace this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you call it contemplation, even if you call it dhamma, it's still replacement, it's still management.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the right recognition of this as suffering, if it's done on the right level, it should be immediately give rise to
[SPEAKER_01]: Anatta, to this is not mine, to letting go, to disappropriation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It shouldn't take like an extra step.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you should see it on the level of, I can't simultaneously know this is suffering and keep holding on to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it feels like that, then that's... that recognition of this is suffering is insufficient.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: Most of the time, that would be... that recognition of this as suffering would just be on the level of this is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It wouldn't be the recognition of... that extends even to pleasant feeling, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's that much more fundamental recognition of unsafety.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's pleasant, it's unsafe, because as soon as you touch it, like by accepting it, you accept everything that
[SPEAKER_01]: It could become later.
[SPEAKER_01]: By accepting it, you accept the pain that it could become later.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you recognize it in that way, you don't have to then let go of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that recognition is the letting go of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said, if you see the first noble truth, whoever sees the first noble truth, sees all the other three.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whoever sees the second noble truth, sees all the other three.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whoever sees the third, sees all the other three, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... Yeah, it's just not, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: The general problem is underestimating the depth of what those truths actually are, and thinking it's like something we already know, or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like when you would think, oh yeah, we already know what suffering is, or something, but not really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not according to this, at least.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... is there anything that could eh... Is there anything that could undermine that right type of happiness?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there anything that can undermine that right kind of happiness?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, no, that's precisely why it's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if we're talking about, let's say, samādhi, which would also be considered one of the right types of happiness, is there anything that could undermine that?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, breaking the precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, I guess on the level of samādhi, it could be things more subtle than that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Giving in to the mental intentions.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just, yeah, kind of taking that pressure that you're already sort of withdrawn from and
[SPEAKER_03]: Kind of letting yourself be pressured by it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Your habits, like, giving in to the habits of...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the reason why I'm saying that is because then, you know, there's... there would usually be the assumption that, okay, you get the right type of happiness through your absorption practice and then there are, like, things in the world that can disturb it, like, you know, there's too much noise around or something, and then that disturbs you and brings you back.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even with that, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Joy of samādhi, which is not permanent, it's a temporary liberation, as it is to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, even that is much more permanent, from a certain point of view, that the joy of meditation techniques that people would get, because
[SPEAKER_01]: It's also... the reason why it leads to full understanding, inevitably, is because it's also not on the level of just a feeling that comes up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even that is already an understanding of feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why there is that verse in the Dhammapada that says, there is no jhāna for one who doesn't have understanding, and there is no understanding for one who doesn't have jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, this whole idea that samatha is just... or samādhi is like this...
[SPEAKER_01]: You can have samatha just by doing these exercises and mantras without any discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that's like a separate thing from vipassana.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's completely not separated by the sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even the pleasure of samādhi, it would depend on you already being independent of feelings to a great degree.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why if someone has experienced that pleasure, that right type of pleasure,
[SPEAKER_01]: They basically have already developed their minds even beyond what's necessary for becoming a sotāpanna, for extreme entry.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because a sotāpanna wouldn't have jhānas.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, sotāpatti doesn't, strictly speaking, depend on being a jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And many suttas would describe how a sotāpanna would be striving to get the jhānas, before that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, if you get that right peace, and you're not a sotāpanna,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, it's not the right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it has to lead in that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you were already able to make yourself independent of feelings to the point where you entered the first jhāna, you basically already... if you already knew the Buddhist teaching, you basically, like, already understood the whole point of the mind development.
[SPEAKER_04]: You already understood how to disconnect yourself from feelings, how to see the
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that somebody then would not be a sotāpanna, that's quite inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, if you haven't heard about craving, well, and so on, well, the
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's say, peace that would be there, you would still, to some extent, have a notion of this is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which was then the case when the Buddha was learning material and immaterial attainments.
[SPEAKER_04]: But now, with the Buddha's teaching being present, that's highly unlikely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like if, just, I mean, the vast majority of people who have put enough effort to have a consistent meditation practice, or dhamma practice, to the point where they would even think
[SPEAKER_01]: that they got jhāna, whether it is the actual jhāna or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no way that they didn't get enough information about the dhamma, so that if it were the actual jhāna, they wouldn't have seen the principle of feelings and how to be independent of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why that right type of pleasure, as the Buddha said, it should be cultivated, it should be sought after, because it's not... even that is already not
[SPEAKER_01]: Just something that comes up, like circumstantially.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it can't happen accidentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's entirely based on understanding the nature of your experience on a certain level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not all the way to Four Noble Truths, but let's say 99% of the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sign of the mind level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sign of the mind, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in what is the mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling and perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you haven't been able to
[SPEAKER_01]: See, that liability to suffering that we're talking about, and you're still just preoccupied with covering it up, it's impossible that you would be able to get jhāna, because that already requires you to to be able to feel and be unmoved by what you feel, fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.